{"tossups": [{"question": "In <em>Curee</em>, Emile Zola argues this man nourished \"one hundred thousand earth movers and stone masons\" with one of his projects. Through Credit Focier [[kreh-DEE foh-SYEH]], this designer funded the demolition of older neighborhoods in the <em>\u00cele de la Cit\u00e9</em> [[eel-duh-lah-see-TEH]] in favor of buildings like the Tribunal of Commerce. As Prefect of the Seine [[SEHN]], this man introduced advertising columns known as <em>Colonne Morris</em>, and he created the <em>Place de l'\u00c9toile</em> [[leh-TWAHL]], a road junction around the Arc d' Triomphe. For the point, name this Frenchman of German descent who undertook the urban renewal of Paris during the the reign of Napoleon III.", "answer": "Baron <b><u>Haussmann</u></b> (or Georges-Eug\u00e8ne <b><u>Haussmann</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "A Puerto Rican street gang in the 1950s adopted this movement's name after viewing the Sidney Poitier [[pwah-TYEH]] movie <em>Something of Value</em>, which is set during this colonial struggle. The protagonist Mugo becomes a hero of this movement after undertaking a hunger strike in a detention center in the novel <em>A Grain of Wheat</em> by native son Ng\u0169g\u0129 wa Thiong'o [[neh-GOO-gee wah-tee-AHN-goh]]. Members of this Kikuyu-dominated political movement were targeted in the Hola massacre after being clubbed to death by British guards. Operation Anvil depopulated Nairobi of, for the point, what political faction which vied for Kenyan independence?", "answer": "<b><u>Mau Mau</u></b> movement (or <b><u>Mau Mau</u></b> Rebellion; accept <b><u>KLFA</u></b>; or <b><u>KANU</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle was part of a larger campaign that sought to avenge the losses of territorial governor Arthur St. Clair. This battle, which was fought along the Maumee River, led to the defeat of Chiefs Little Turtle and Blue Jacket. The Treaty of Greenville was signed following the aftermath of this battle, which ended the Northwest Indian War. For the point, identify this 1794 battle in which Anthony Wayne defeated a confederacy of Native Americans.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Fallen Timbers</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After the Achaean League general Diaeus [[dee-AY-ooss]] set up camp here following the Battle of Scarpheia, this city was razed by Lucius Mummius. The first meeting of the Hellenic League, formed by Philip of Macedon against Persia following the Battle of Chaeronea [[kay-ruh-NAY-uh]], was held at this city, which sometimes gives the league its name. The King's Peace ended a war named for this city that broke out shortly after the Peloponnesian War and pitted Sparta against a Greek-Persian alliance. Tyrants such as Periander of the Cypselid dynasty ruled, for the point, what Greek city that hosted the Isthmian Games?", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b> (or <b><u>K\u00f3rinth</u></b>os; accept League of <b><u>Corinth</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Ekoji I founded a kingdom subservient to this empire and attempted to seize the Coleroon River region from his brother, a ruler of this realm named Shivaji. With assistance from the Rohilla, the Pashtun Durrani Empire halted this state's expansion during the Third Battle of Panipat. A refusal to accept the results of the Battle of Wadagon led to this Hindu empire's first war with the British East India company. The <em>Peshwa</em> ruled, for the point, what Confederacy which eclipsed the Mughals in power on the Indian subcontinent in the 18th century?", "answer": "<b><u>Maratha</u></b> Confederacy (or <b><u>Maratha</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Though this man was nominally Pasteur Bizimungu's vice president, he held the real power of his country during two wars against his country's large western neighbor, once called Zaire. This man led a rebellion from Uganda and opposed the hate speech of RTLM and the <em>Interahamwe</em> militia. This man's country has been referred to as the \"Singapore of Africa\" for its recovery after the brutal 1994 massacres of the Tutsi people, of which this man is a member. For the point, name this president of Rwanda since 2000.", "answer": "Paul <b><u>Kagame</u></b> [[kah-GAH-meh]]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The U.S. Socialist Workers Party published an article concerning an attempt at this action titled <em>The Murder of Bob Harte</em>. Muralist David Alfaro Siqueiros [[see-KEH-rohss]] made an attempt at this action with NKVD agent Joseph Grigulevich, resulting in the target's nephew, Esteban, being shot in the foot. A Spanish-born agent successfully committed this action, for which he was awarded the Order of Lenin by Leonid Brezhnev [[BRESH-nehf]]. Ram\u00f3n Mercader [[rah-MOHN mehr-KAH-dehr]] used an ice-axe to commit, for the point, what 1940 hit-job on a rival of Joseph Stalin in Mexico?", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of Leon <b><u>Trotsky</u></b> (accept equivalents like <b><u>kill</u></b>ing <b><u>Trotsky</u></b>; accept Lev <b><u>Bronstein</u></b> in place of Leon <b><u>Trotsky</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Two answers required. A planned invasion of one of these countries by the other was known as Operation Sovereignty. The de-escalation of an arms race between these two countries was a goal of the Pacts of May. During the Baltimore Crisis, a minister in one of these countries offered the U.S. access to a base in Salta in order to attack the other. During the Snipe incident, the navy of one of these countries attacked the other's lighthouse in the Beagle Channel. For the point, name these two countries which fought over colonization of Patagonia.", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u></b> and <b><u>Chile</u></b> (accept <b><u>Argentine</u></b> Republic or Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Argentina</u></b> in place of <b><u>Argentina</u></b>; accept Republic of <b><u>Chile</u></b> or Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Chile</u></b> in place of <b><u>Chile</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After clerking for Arthur Goldberg, this justice served as a fact-checker for the Warren Commission. In a 2005 book, this justice reinterpreted two central concepts of an Isaiah Berlin essay. This author of <em>Active Liberty</em> authored a 2021 opinion in which he found that Google\u2019s copying of 0.4% of the Java code constituted \u201cfair use.\" This man rose to the Supreme Court as Harry Blackmun\u2019s successor in 1994. For the point, name this Supreme Court Justice who in January 2022 announced his plan to retire.", "answer": "Stephen <b><u>Breyer</u></b> (or Stephen Gerald <b><u>Breyer</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Following the call for an armistice during this war, Guiseppe Garbaldi said the one word phrase \"Obbedisco\" [[oh-beh-DEE-skoh]], or \"I Obey!\" following the Battle of Bezzecca [[beh-TSEH-kah]]. This war's Treaty of London gave back the region of Venetia and Frulia to the Kingdom of Italy. One side's deployment of infantry wielding needle guns allowed Helmuth von Moltke's forces to outgun their opponent in this war's Battle of K\u00f6niggr\u00e4tz [[KEHR-nih-grahts]]. A dispute over Schleswig-Holstein led to, for the point, what war between the North German Confederation and the Habsburg monarchy?", "answer": "<b><u>Austro-Prussia</u></b>n War (accept the <b><u>Seven Week</u></b>s' War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person was represented by Fred Gray in one case, alongside fellow plaintiffs Marie Louise Smith and Susie McDonald. That case sued W. A. Gayle, mayor of a city where this woman performed a notable action nine months before a similar incident. This plaintiff in <em>Browder v. Gayle</em> was likely unsupported by the wider Civil Rights movement due to being unmarried and pregnant. For the point, name this woman who refused to give up her seat on a Montgomery, Alabama bus before Rosa Parks.", "answer": "Claudette <b><u>Colvin</u></b> (or Claudette <b><u>Austin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this nation, a protest erupted outside the headquarters of the Construction, Forestry, Maritime, Mining, and Energy Union in response to the vaccine mandate placed on construction workers. The Minister for the Environment of this nation was taken to court by a group of teenagers and a nun to halt the expansion of the Vickery coal mine. Alex Hawke rejected an athlete\u2019s visa to this country because he was \u201ca talisman of anti-vaccination sentiment.\u201d Novak Djokovic [[JOH-koh-vitch]] was deported from, for the point, what country led by Prime Minister Scott Morrison?", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Australia</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man's father-in-law, Lucius Aemilius Paullus, legendarily killed the mercenary captain Viriathus. This man's tombstone, which reads \"Ungrateful fatherland, you will not even have my bones,\" was erected due to bitterness at his exile from Rome after being falsely charged with taking bribes from Antiochus the Great. The death of this man's father at Upper Baetis by Hasdrubal prompted this general to undertake the Hispania campaign of the Second Punic War. For the point, name this victor at Zama who was given the honorific <em>Africanus</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Scipio Africanus</u></b> the Elder (or <b><u>Scipio Africanus</u></b> Major; accept Publius Cornelius <b><u>Scipio Africanus</u></b>; accept <b><u>Scipio</u></b> alone after \"Africanus\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "With fellow abolitionist Granville Sharp, this man made a 1777 plea to the Crown of England to end its protracted \"War in Thirteen Colonies.\" This man, who refused the governorship of the Carolinas, defeated an invasion by the Spanish under Antonio Barba at the Battle of Bloody Marsh during the War of Jenkins' Ear. This man advocated for an excise tax on malt liquor to fund a comprehensive reform of the prison system of England while head of the Gaols [[\"JAILS\"]] Committee. Georgia was founded as a debtor's colony by, for the point, which British member of Parliament?", "answer": "James Edward <b><u>Oglethorpe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "With assistance from the BfV, this agency killed liaison officer Atef Bseiso [[beh-SEH-soh]] while in Paris despite the recent Oslo Accord negotiations. This organization successfully orchestrated the death of Ali Hassan Salameh, the Red Prince, during the larger \"Operation Wrath of God.\" This agency undertook an extrajudicial operation which captured and led to the execution of Adolf Eichmann after he was discovered hiding in Argentina. For the point, name this intelligence agency of the State of Israel.", "answer": "<b><u>Mossad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was said to have saved three innocent men from execution by pushing the executioner\u2019s sword to the ground. The medieval tradition in which a boy parodies a bishop, takes control of the cathedral, and performs clerical duties was in celebration of this man. One tradition observed in the Netherlands during this man\u2019s \u201cFeast\u201d involves children putting carrots and hay in their shoes as gifts for his horse. For the point, what Bishop of Myra is the patron saint of children and the inspiration for Santa Claus?", "answer": "Saint <b><u>Nicholas</u></b> of Myra (or <b><u>Nicholas</u></b> of Bari; or Sint-<b><u>Nicolaas</u></b>; or Sankt <b><u>Nikolaus</u></b>; accept <b><u>Saint Nick</u></b>; accept \u201cBishop of Myra\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "During this event, former medic Donald Hohman went on a month-long hunger strike. Prime Minister of Canada Joe Clark allowed an Order of Council letting Canadian passports be issued to some American citizens during this event. Operation Eagle Claw was a failed attempt to end this event, which was perpetrated by a Muslim student organization under the influence of Ayatollah Khomeini. The Election of Ronald Reagan influenced the end of, for the point, which \"Crisis\" caused by a takeover of the U.S. embassy in Tehran?", "answer": "<b><u>Iran Hostage</u></b> Crisis", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a speech about this conflict, Wilhelm II declared that a certain group \u201cwill [never] ever again dare to look cross-eyed at a German.\u201d Some of the clauses in a \u201cProtocol\u201d ending this conflict included an apology to the German emperor for Baron von Ketteler\u2019s assassination and the destruction of the Taku Forts. This conflict was formally ordered by Empress Dowager Cixi [[SEE-SHEE]]. Won by the Eight-Nation Alliance, for the point, what anti-foreign \u201cRebellion\u201d in China was named after the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists?", "answer": "<b><u>Boxer</u></b> Rebellion (or <b><u>Boxer</u></b> Uprising; or <b><u>Boxer</u></b> Resurrection; or <b><u>Yihetuan</u> </b>Movement)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A draft of this proposal mentioned that members of the House of Representatives would hold three-year terms while those in the Senate would have seven-year terms. This proposal was presented by Edmund Randolph as a fifteen-point resolution to the Constitutional Convention in 1787. Drafted by James Madison, for the point, what proposal, later countered by the New Jersey Plan, advocated for the establishment of a bicameral legislature and three branches of government?", "answer": "<b><u>Virginia</u></b> Plan (accept <b><u>Large-State</u></b> Plan; accept <b><u>Randolph</u></b> Plan before \u201cEdmund Randolph\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these locations was the birthplace of a character who steals a necklace from a child and reconnects with her \"Lancashire husband.\" Most of Thomas Malory's <em>Le Morte</em> <em>d'Arthur</em> [[dahr-TUHR]] was likely written at one of these locations. The protagonist's mother \"pleads the belly\" while at one of these places in <em>Moll Flanders</em>. A resident of one of these places wrote a letter to the son of the Marquess of Queensbury and a poem that notes, \"Each man kills the thing he loves.\" For the point, name these locations about which Oscar Wilde wrote while facing punishment for homosexuality.", "answer": "<b><u>Prison</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Jail</u></b>s or <b><u>Gaol</u></b>s; accept specific prisons like Newgate <b><u>Prison</u></b> or Reading <b><u>Gaol</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Much of this nation's territory was gained from the Tati Concessions by Matabele king Lobengula [[loh-BEN-goo-lah]] for arms and gold bullion. Stellaland was a failed Boer state established in this modern-day nation, which was supported by the Transvaal Republic until the Warren Expedition captured Mafeking [[mah-feh-KING]]. Most of Namibia's Herero people fled to this modern nation after facing systemic genocide by German occupiers. Known as Bechuanaland under British colonial rule, for the point, what is this African nation governed from Gabarone?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Botswana</u></b> (or Lefatshe la <b><u>Botswana</u></b>; accept <b><u>Bechuanaland</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The U.S. government created special coins which could not transmit this disease for the Palo Seco region of the Panama Canal Zone. The term \"Lazaretto,\" a medieval location used to isolate potential plague victims, derives its name from the biblical Lazarus the Beggar, who was affected by this disease. King Kamehameha V created a \"colony\" for people effected by this disease on the island of Kalaupapa, which is where Saint Damien of Molokai served afflicted people. Wild armadillos can spread, for the point, what historically persecuted disease which causes skin lesions?", "answer": "<b><u>Leprosy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Leper</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Leper</u></b> colony)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This opera's title character notes, \"They were all lying! All of them!\" after realizing that a ship is the USS <em>Abraham Lincoln</em>. The aria \"Dovunque [[doh-VOON-keh]] al Mondo\" features motifs of the \"Star-Spangled Banner\" in this opera. That motif in this opera accompanies a character who marries Kate, prompting the protagonist to give her son an American flag and kill herself. For the point, name this Giacomo Puccini opera about a woman who marries American Lieutenant B.F. Pinkerton, Cio-Cio [[CHO-CHO]] San.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Madama Butterfly</u></b></em> (accept <em><b><u>Madame Butterfly</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "Anchored off the coast of this non-U.S. city, the U.S. Navy lost the USS <em>Memphis</em> after 70-foot rogue waves wrecked it during repairs. Rear Admiral William Caperton's threats to bombard this city led the government of Desiderio Arias to flee, leading to an eight-year U.S. occupation. U.S. agents supported Joaqu\u00edn Balaguer [[wah-KEEN bah-lah-GEHR]] loyalists who fought for control of this city after the death of a leader who committed the Parsley Massacre. For the point, name this city from which Rafael Trujillo [[troo-HEE-yoh]] ruled the Dominican Republic.", "answer": "<b><u>Santo Domingo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "While facing a paternity suit against Joan Berry, this man was charged by the FBI under J. Edgar Hoover with violating the Mann Act. This person was accused of being a communist by Mississippi congressman John Rankin, who also called for his deportation. After over twenty years of exile, this person returned to the United States in 1972 to accept an Honorary Oscar. For the point, what British silent film actor is best known for films such as <em>City Lights</em>, <em>Modern Times</em>, and <em>The Great Dictator</em>?", "answer": "Charlie <b><u>Chaplin</u></b> (or Charles Spencer <b><u>Chaplin</u></b> Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person and Gregory Bateson produced a short documentary about the Kris Dance, a ritual practiced in Balinese culture. Derek Freeman called this person a \u201cfateful hoaxing\u201d for being duped by indigenous interviewees. This person argued that adolescents in Western cultures faced \u201cstorm and stress\u201d compared to those living on the island of Ta\u2019\u016b. For the point, what cultural anthropologist who advocated for a broadening of sexual attitudes wrote <em>Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies</em> and <em>Coming of Age in</em> <em>Samoa</em>?", "answer": "Margaret <b><u>Mead</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "This man set up a base of operations at Snow's Island along the Pee Dee River and defeated a group of Loyalist militiamen at the Battle of Black Mingo. Colonel Banastre Tarleton was tasked with killing this man, whose use of territory between the Santee and Pee Dee Rivers to escape led to his nickname. For the point, name this Continental soldier whose extensive use of guerilla tactics in his native South Carolina earned him the nickname \"The Swamp Fox.\u201d", "answer": "Francis <b><u>Marion</u></b> (accept <b><u>Swamp Fox</u></b> before read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A music video of a George Michael song depicts this person behaving like a dog while playing with a U.S. president on the White House lawn. This person said he \u201cacted in good faith\u201d after the Chilcot Report exposed his initial downplay of the war in Iraq. This man and Bertie Ahern signed the Good Friday Agreement less than a year into his premiership. Described as being George W. Bush\u2019s \u201cpoodle\u201d, for the point, what Labour Party leader was prime minister of the United Kingdom from 1997 to 2007?", "answer": "Tony <b><u>Blair</u></b> (or Anthony Charles Lynton <b><u>Blair</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "According to Martin P. Nilsson, this woman was worshipped as a vegetation goddess on the island of Rhodes. A song created by Theocritus [[thee-AH-krih-tuss]] as a wedding commemoration includes the line, \u201cReverence me. I am [this woman\u2019s] tree.\u201d This woman was believed to have been buried in the town of Therapne, in which she shares a shrine with Menelaus. For the point, what woman in Greek mythology was known as \u201cthe face that launched a thousand ships,\u201d whose elopement with Paris caused the Trojan War?", "answer": "<b><u>Helen</u></b> of Troy", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "In 2016, a group of scholars discovered that these events occurred at what is now a Walgreens parking lot. A person was charged in these events after a woman named Mercy Lewis claimed she couldn\u2019t unclasp her hands. These events were recorded in a book titled <em>Wonders of the Invisible World</em> by Cotton Mather, who influenced the execution of Ann Glover. Mary Eastey, Rebecca Nurse, and John Proctor were some of the victims of, for the point, what 1692 \u201ctrials\u201d that caused a mass hysteria in Massachusetts over the presence of supernatural beings?", "answer": "<b><u>Salem witch</u></b> trials (prompt on \u201cwitch trials\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The historian Xenophon [[ZEN-uh-fen]] attributes the birth of this profession to the failed usurper Cyrus the Younger, who instituted it while serving as <em>satrap</em> of the remote region of Ionia. Augustus introduced the <em>anabasii</em> system composed of men in this profession who made use of chariots. Incan men in this profession known as <em>chasquis</em> [[CHAH-skeess]] chewed on coca plants to assist their endurance. Pheidippides [[fy-DIP-ih-dees]] served in, for the point, what role while telling Athens the news of the Greek victory at Marathon?", "answer": "<b><u>Courier</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Runner</u></b>s; or <b><u>Messenger</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Mailman</u></b>; accept obvious equivalents)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man is the subject of a woman's comment in a 2020 film toward a group of caged monkeys, \u201cNobody but nobody makes a monkey out of [this man],\" while in conversation with Herman J. Mankiewicz [[MANK-yeh-witz]]. A film based on this man depicts his unsuccessful run to become the governor of New York. That same 1941 film depicts a woman named Susan Alexander embarking on an amateur opera career, paralleling this man\u2019s influence on the career of his real-life mistress, Marion Davies. For the point, what media tycoon was the primary inspiration for Charles Foster Kane in the film <em>Citizen Kane</em>?", "answer": "William Randolph <b><u>Hearst</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "The construction of this structure was interrupted after its city\u2019s defeat in the Battle of Meloria. Despite confirming the presence of German troops at this structure, U.S. Army sergeant Leon Weckstein prevented it from being targeted by an artillery strike after finding it too beautiful to destroy. Galileo Galilei supposedly tested his law of free fall by dropping two cannonballs of different masses from this structure. For the point, what landmark in Pisa, Italy is tilted at nearly four degrees?", "answer": "<b><u>Leaning Tower</u></b> of Pisa (or <b><u>Torre Pendente</u></b> di Pisa)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person once asked, \u201cWhen will mankind be convinced that true religion is from the heart?\u201d This person called Alexander Hamilton a \u201cman ambitious as Julius Caesar\u201d before writing, \u201cI have ever kept my eye upon him.\u201d This person wrote another letter asking to \u201cremember the ladies and be more generous and favorable to them than your ancestors.\u201d A prolific writer, for the point, what First Lady was the wife and mother to the second and sixth presidents of the United States, respectively?", "answer": "<b><u>A</u></b>bigail <b><u>Adams</u></b> (prompt on \u201cAdams\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Despite effectively losing the Livonian War, this ruler centralized rule around his person by dismantling the \"Chosen Council.\" This man's <em>oprichniki</em> [[oh-preech-NEE-kee]] secret police committed the massacre of Novgorod and conducted a mass repression of the Boyars. For the point, name this \"fearsome\" grand prince of Moscow who declared himself the first Tsar of All Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivan the Terrible</u></b> (or <b><u>Ivan Grozny</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ivan IV</u></b> Vasilyevich; prompt on \"Ivan\")  <b>Extra Questions </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A visit to this city by a Norwegian delegation led by diplomat Jonas Gahr St\u00f8re [[YOO-nas GAR STOO-ruh]] prompted a contingent of the Haqqani [[hah-KAHN-ee]] network to attack the Serana Hotel. Beginning in the Shari Naw neighborhood of this city, the Saur Revolution overthrew Mohammed Daoud Khan and killed him after he refused to pledge allegiance to the Soviet aligned Communist Party. A mid-1990s siege of this city culminated in the hanging of former president Mohammad Najibullah outside the Arg Presidential Palace. The Taliban retook, for the point, what capital of Afghanistan in 2021?", "answer": "<b><u>Kabul</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}